<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lavv out lavved or, The charter of the Gospell shewing the priviledge and prerogative of the saints by vertue of the covenant Wherein these foure points of doctrine are properly observed, plainely proved, both by Scripture, and reason: and pithily applyed. Viz: doctrine 1 That he that is in the state of grace lyeth in no knowne sinne, no sinne hath dominion over him. 2 That sinne though it doth not raigne in the saints, yet it doth remaine and dwell in them. 3 That the way to overcome sinne, is to get assurance of the love, and grace, and favour of God, whereby it is forgiven them. 4 That whosoever is under the law, sinne hath dominion over him. By that late faithfull and worthy minister of Iesus Christ. Iohn Preston. Doctor in divinity, chaplaine in ordinary to his Majestie, master of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge, and sometimes preacher of Lincolnes Inne.</title>
            <author>Preston, John, 1587-1628.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110464</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10940</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10940)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1668:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lavv out lavved or, The charter of the Gospell shewing the priviledge and prerogative of the saints by vertue of the covenant Wherein these foure points of doctrine are properly observed, plainely proved, both by Scripture, and reason: and pithily applyed. Viz: doctrine 1 That he that is in the state of grace lyeth in no knowne sinne, no sinne hath dominion over him. 2 That sinne though it doth not raigne in the saints, yet it doth remaine and dwell in them. 3 That the way to overcome sinne, is to get assurance of the love, and grace, and favour of God, whereby it is forgiven them. 4 That whosoever is under the law, sinne hath dominion over him. By that late faithfull and worthy minister of Iesus Christ. Iohn Preston. Doctor in divinity, chaplaine in ordinary to his Majestie, master of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge, and sometimes preacher of Lincolnes Inne.</title>
                  <author>Preston, John, 1587-1628.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wreittoun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "I That he that .. over him." are bracketed together with three brackets on title page, with the word "doctrine" reading down to the left.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The law outlawed.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10940:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10940:1"/>
            <p>THE LAW OVT LAVVED OR, The Charter of the Goſpell ſhewing the priviledge and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the Saints by vertue of the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein theſe foure points of doctrine are properly obſerved, <hi>Plainely proved, both by Scripture and reaſon: and pithily applyed. VIZ:</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Doctrine</head>
               <item>1 That he that is in the ſtate of grace lyeth in no knowne ſinne, no ſinne hath dominion over him.</item>
               <item>2 That ſinne though it doth not raigne in the Saints, yet it doth remaine and dwell in them.</item>
               <item>3 That the way to overcome ſinne, is to get aſſurance of the Love, and grace, and favour of God, whereby it is forgiven them.</item>
               <item>4 That whoſoever is under the Law, ſinne hath dominion over him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By that late faithfull and worthy Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt. IOHN PRESTON.</p>
            <p>Doctor in divinity, Chaplaine in ordinary to his Majeſtie, Maſter of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge, and ſometimes preacher of Lincolnes Inne.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let not ſinne therefore raigne in your mortall bodies, that you ſhould obey the lusts thereof,</p>
               <bibl>Rom. 6. 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>EDINBVRGH Printed by Iohn Wreittoun. 1633.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:10940:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10940:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Romans.</hi> 6. 14.</bibl>
               <q>For ſinne ſhall not have dominion over you, for you are not under the law, but under grace.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are brought in thus, the Apoſtle exhortes them not to ſinne, but to give their members as inſtruments unto righteouſnes, and to move them to this, he tels them that ſin was not their Lord now as it was heeretofore, and that it ſhall have no more dominion over them, and therefore he bids them ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: and then he adds a reaſon of this, becauſe they were not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law, but under grace, now Chriſt hath changed their hearts, for while a man is under the Law, ſinne hath dominion over him, it tels him what to doe, but gives him no power to doe it, but you have the grace of ſanctification to change your hearts, and enable you to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good word and worke, ſo that you delight in the Law, after the inner man, albeit you ſee another law in your members roaring againſt the Law in your minde, and bringing you into captivity to the law of ſin, which is your members, as it is ſaid, in the 7. chapter, and the 23. verſe.</p>
            <p>Whence wee may learne?<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct, </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>That hee that is in the ſtate of grace, lyeth in no knowne ſinne, no ſinne hath dominion over him.</p>
            <p>Now ſinne is ſaid to have no Dominion over a man, three manner of wayes, viz. in regard</p>
            <p>Q It hath no right to rule over him, it is no more our Lord, but is as a ſervant that hath no dominion, but is ſaid to offer violence to us, as if the King of Spaine ſhould rule over us, he hath no dominion over us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In regard its not obeyed, for there it hath dominion, as a Prince may have right to a kingdome, yet he be not obeyed, he hath no dominion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly in regard though it ſtrive againſt us, yet it never gets the victory, for though it a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> us, yet if it g<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not the victory it hath no
<pb facs="tcp:10940:3"/>
dominion over us, this is proved by their ſimilitudes which muſt bee explained. viz.</p>
            <p>Firſt it was our Maſter and we its ſervants, but n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w we have chang<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed our Maſters, and are become the ſervants of righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly it is ſaid that we were married to ſinne, and it had domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ. </seg>8,</label> and command over us, as the husband over the wife, but now it is dead, and there is a divorce betweene us, and now wee are married to Chriſt and hee commands us, and wee obey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly it is ſaid we were dead to ſinne and alive to God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſe </seg>6,</label> we cannot live in ſinne, for command a dead body to goe about a buſſineſſe, and hee cannot, becauſe hee is dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> Now the reaſons of the point bee theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the is taken from Chriſt, all wee are ingrafted into Chriſt, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> into his death, and into the ſimilituds of his reſurrection, verſe. 5. that we are grafted as a graft into Chriſt and all the old ſappes taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and we have new ſap, and bring foorth new fruite, and have no other, becauſe we grow in another tree, and wee live to God, yet wee may commit ſinne though we allow not our ſelves in it, for they that are in Chriſt have crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if therefore there be any luſt in him he is not Chriſt. Againe if any man bee in Chriſt he is new creature: and therefore he doth not wallow in hisould ſinnes, ſo ſaith God I will give you a new heart, and all things are become new, and old things are done away, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee cannot lye in any knowne ſinne.</p>
            <p>Againe whoſoever is in Chriſt hath receaved of his fullnes grace for grace, in him we are able to doe all things, and therefore if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtrive againſt old ſinnes, wee are not in Chriſt, and therefore wee muſt ſtrive to bee compleat.</p>
            <p>Secondly becauſe we have the Spirit of God ruling in us, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> we walke after the Spirit, and not after the fleſh, now if wee lye in any knowne ſinne, we have not the Spirit, and therefore are not in the ſtate of grace, if any man have not the Spirit of grace, he is not the Sonne of God, now if he walke after the fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he hath not the Spirit, for the ſpirit gives him ability to ſtrive againſt all ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he is borne of God, now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee that is borne of God ſinneth not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, it ruleth not over him, for a man is ſaid to ſinne that favours wickednes, and ſetteth his heart to ſinne, he ſinneth not, becauſe he is like God, as a ſonne is like his father, and therefore a wicked man is like the devill, becauſe hee is his Father, and his wickednes is in him, and therefore the devill is called the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather of the wicked: and ſo every
<pb facs="tcp:10940:3"/>
regenerat man hath all the righteouſnes of Chriſt, though not in the ſame degree, he hath perfective holynes of parts, though not of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, now then he hath no member of Satan in him, that is, no known ſinne which hee loveth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe he hath the whole law written in his heart, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> his heart is ſet to obey the whole law, and therefore he cannot lye in any knowne ſinne.</p>
            <p>Fifthly becauſe hee is wholly changed and tranſlated to another man <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> which is expreſt two wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest</hi> The whole drift of his minde is changed, as ſuppoſe the earth were made fire, the whole vent of it were to goe upward, ſo a man is wholly bent towards heaven, or els his heart is not changed, and if ſo, hee can lye in no knowne ſinne.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, he is changed in his taſt, S. Paul ſaith they that are in Chriſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> ſavour not the things of the fleſh, but of the ſpirit, every ſinne is bitter to the regenerate man, if it bee not then hee ſavoureth the things of the fleſh, to this is that agreable, keepe this feaſt with vnleavened bread, and not with old leaven of maliciouſnes, we muſt be unleavened bread to Chriſt: wee muſt give no allowance to ſinne.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Becauſe they know God, Ier. 33. The Lord ſaith by his <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> Prophet, I will write my law in their hearts, and they ſhall know mee ſo that with this wryting, the law in their hearts they cannot but know ſinne, for they are changed in their minds before that they can know God: hence I inferre that hee that knowes God will not change from the immutable God to the mutable creature, and they that doe it, doe it becauſe they know not God.</p>
            <p>Eightly, becauſe hee hath faith, which will make us not lye in any knowne ſinne, for all ſinnes are either of the temptation of the devill, the fleſh, or the world, now faith overcomes all theſe,</p>
            <p>1 It overcommeth the world; This is the victory that overcometh the world, even your ſaith, but if the world could overcome the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate in any temptation, then this were not true, that faith over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the world, but he ſhall not be overcome, by the glory and riches of the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the fleſh, the juſt walketh in his integritie, to this added that bleſſings are every where annexed to the keeping of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, bleſſed are they that have reſpect unto the com<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if you leane to the right <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, or to the left y<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, againe if you keepe the whole law and off<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are guilty of the whole law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:4"/>
But, beſides theſe ſcriptures there bee other reaſons to prove that the regenerat man cannot lye in any knowne ſinne,</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe hee that lyes in any knowne ſinne: hath another for his <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> Lord and God, and ſo is an Idolater, and ſo cannot bee regenerate, for hee yeeldeth to the ſame ſtill, if it commands, hee obeyeth, God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him, hee neglecteth it, and therefore maketh it his God.</p>
            <p>Secondly becauſe he lyeth in any knowne ſinne, will be unconſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> in the ſerving of God, now God rejecteth ſuch an one, for though the temptation to that ſinne, being removed hee ſerve God, yet that ſinne ſetting upon him, hee forſakes Gods ſervice, and obeyeth it, and when ſoever occaſion is offered, he turneth to obey it, now ſuch unconſtancy God hateth, as among m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a flower though it more beautyfull then a pearle, yet it is not regarded ſo much becauſe it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ading, and a ſhippe may ſaile ſafe a great while, but yet falling upon a rocke maketh ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of faith and good conſcience, and ſuch a one cannot bee in the ſtate of grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe hee that lyeth in any knowne ſinne, will if hee had <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> like ſtrong temptations commit all the ſinnes in the world, as bee a man inclined to covetouſnes or uncle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he would commit any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if hee were as much inclined to any other, now ſuch an one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee in the ſtate of grace.</p>
            <p>Fourthly becauſe if a man have a good hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, no ſin can grow there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe it is out of its proper place, and therefore cannot proſper as plants that grow in India if they bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tt heere wither, ſo every ſinne i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a good heart is out of its proper place and wil not grow but wither every day more and more, but he that findeth ſinne growing in his heart, his heart is not regenerat.</p>
            <p>Fiftly becauſe he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt hate the word of God and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> when a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ready to commit ſinne, the word i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to diſſwade him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> godly men diſſwade him, and therefore now if hee doe it and they ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>buke him, hee commeth to account the word a reproach a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d hee hates it and good men likewiſe, Thus <hi>Iohn</hi> is <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds</hi> friend a great while, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tels him of his beloved ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>f goes head, ſo they hate God and wiſh that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>re were none, becauſe hee reſolveth to ſinne, and God reproves him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee in a good eſtate:</p>
            <p>Sixtly and laſtly, becauſe all his actions will have an evill tincture <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> from that his ſin, it ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yeth all he doth, ſo that nothing is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight. As if a man were ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o get honour, though he did not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly fall into that ſinne, yet he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:4"/>
affecteth ſuch perſons that may further that his intent ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veneth every action of his, and whenſoever any act of religion oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, he then forſaketh all, as if a man have a project to get a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt that is not yet come, all that hee doth is for that end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ploweth, ſoweth, and the like, ſo it is with a man that hath a ſinne and reſolves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llow it, he by-uſeth all his actions by that, therefore God abhorres him: and all that he doth.</p>
            <p>Firſt this is to try us, every man may know if he bee in the ſtate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> grace or no, if he lyes in the leaſt knowne ſinne that is, he is but coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, if though he be admoniſhed and told, that God will not have him to doe ſuch a thing, yet he doth it: its a ſigne hee is not in a good eſtate, as if a man knew, and were perſwaded, he ought not to abound in idle ſpeeches, and yet will, it is a ſigne he is not in the ſtate of grace, ſo when he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded he ought to pray and yet doth it not, or doth it only for ſhew, its a ſigne he is in a bad eſtate, for if hee knew its a ſinne to be idle, and it comes into his minde that he ſhould not, and is perſwaded of it, and yet will; its a ſigne his eſtate is not good, ſo as for immodera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaming, if one be told he ſhould not, yet will vſe it, all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is naught, certainely hee is bad, ſo for the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, when a man ſhall ſpend all his time, and find all his thoughts bent that way for any one of them, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is his heart is not gracious, for then theſe thoughts would not abound in him, but thoughts of growing in grace, but if his morning thoughts be for ſatisfying of the fleſh and the luſts thereof, or his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets plots, he may juſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare its a reigning ſinne, for when all his projects and thoughts, are upon one thing, as to bee in fine apparell, its certaine ſinne reigneth in him, and ſo he is in the ſtate of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a ſcholer that wholly aimes at vaine glory, and how to get ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and credit, that ſin reigneth in him.</p>
            <p>But there were many which ſeemed religious men which had theſe <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ, </seg>
               </label> infirmities in them in the ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>True, and many therefore not truely regenerated but ſeeming only <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ, </seg>
               </label> ſo, now many youths make a faire ſhow, under the meanes, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into temptations fall away, but if they be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded or thinke of it, great faults may ſtand with true grace, but if they be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>moniſhed by their conſcience or others, and told they muſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doe it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their eſtate is not good, for true grace cannot ſtand with theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ailings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the ſignes whereby wee may know, whether we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> live in known ſinnes or not, are theſe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:5"/>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Living in a knowne ſinne is of two ſorts, firſt knowne, when me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell themſelves to commit wickednes before the Lord as <hi>Ahab</hi> did, when he poureth out himſelfe to vanity, as when a man ſhall give up himſelfe to drinke or to company, or to commit any ſin of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or giveth himſelfe to ſpend any of his time in recreations, this is evident to the world and to his owne conſcience. Againe when he plainely forſaketh God and good courſes which hee tooke before, as <hi>Demas</hi> did, this is plaine, he lyeth in a knowne ſinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly the ſecret lying in ſin, the ſignes whereof are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt</hi> When a man committeth it ordinarily, this is that Paul ſaith that the ſaints fall upon occaſions, as if a man be ſailing into <hi>France,</hi> a tempeſt driveth him into Spaine, ſo the Saints face is towards heaven but a ſuddaine paſſion may drive them another way: to commit ſinne ordinarily, is to commit it when temptation aſſaileth, and occaſion is offered, and impediments removed, then hee commits the ſinne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, for if there were ſuch temptations alwayes, he would commit the ſinne alwayes, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> was good by fits, he was often reſtored, &amp; deſired them to pray for him, yet when temptation came he would not let the people goe, though before he had intended to doe it. So <hi>Saul</hi> when opportunitie was offered, would have killed <hi>David,</hi> thogh he ſwore not to doe it, and ſo <hi>Hazael,</hi> this is committing of ſinnes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily.<note place="margin">Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, When a man rejecteth admonitions, and the reprover, a poore Child is better<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then a fooliſh (that is a rich) King that will no longer bee admoniſhed, for then his heart is evill, for if a man bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have his luſt mortified, he is well pleaſed with him that brings him a knife to cut it off, becauſe he doth as he would have him to doe but when they are purpoſed to ly in ſinne, they doe as a man doth with Phyſick that hee loatheth, he hateth even the very pot it ſelfe, wherein it was, ſo they hate them that admoniſh them even as dogs, but if they can indure the company of good men it is a ſigne his heart is good.</p>
            <p>Thirdly Abſtinence from occaſions, for many ſay their infirmities make them runne into ſuch and ſuch ſinnes, but if they were minded to leave their ſinnes, they may leave their euill company and all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to this adde the uſe of the meanes, for hee that purpoſeth to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke his ſinnes will uſe the meanes, as if a man that is a drunkard, will keep drunkards company, he hath purpoſed to forſake his ſinnes, for then he would forſake and leave his evill company, but if hee uſe the mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es for mortyfying his ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he loveth, then it is a ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:10940:5"/>
to leave ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the meanes for mortifying ſinfull luſts in us, are theſe. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to make a vow not to commit that ſinne, nor touch the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, for then it is a ſigne his heart is ſincere, this is a comfort to theſe that have made vowes, which ſhould be more uſed, not to make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall vowes, but for ſome ſhort tyme.</p>
            <p>Secondly to faſt, and pray, for ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owes</hi> luſts are not caſt out by theſe three, to uſe godly meanes company, for their practiſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample helpes them to forſake their ſinnes, to faſt and pray.</p>
            <p>Thirdly another ſigne of lying in known ſinne, is when a man prayes for admonitions that God would ſtirre up ſome to admoniſh him, and can bee content to ſearch out reaſons out of the Scripture againſt it, &amp; is glad when he heares it reproved in the publique miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when hee can be content to be deprived of many things which might further our luſts, and to loath what ſweetnes which might encreaſe them, that is a ſure ſigne that ſinne rules not in us.</p>
            <p>Fiftly when a man con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſeth his ſinnes particularly, and plainely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for this is a ſigne hee would forſake them, this reaſon the Scripture doth ſhow, becauſe then the conſcience maketh ſuch a noyſe, that hee cannot deny it, for when a man is purpoſed to continue in ſinne, he will not confeſſe his ſinnes, no not to GOD, it is ſaid when they came to<note place="margin">Math, 3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal, 23, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, they con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſed their ſinnes. So <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>when I ſaid I will confeſſe my ſinne, the Lord forgiveth the wickedneſſe of my ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, When he is eaſily convicted, but when men will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed but ſeeke out diſtinctions to maintaine their ſinne, it is a ſigne it is prevalent in them. Againe when they will not examine both ſides, but runne to commit it, and ſtop their eares like the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e adder, which refuſeth to heare the voice of the Charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely, and will not heare the reaſons againſt that ſin, leaſt he ſhould be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, therefore the righteous are ſaid to ponder their wayes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their paths, and to try every thing, &amp; to take that which is good, now he that wil but heare reaſons againſt the ſinne he doth, he is none of theſe, but when he will not be convinced, which is the firſt worke of the ſpirit, it is a ſigne he is under the dominion of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, when a man abſtaineth from ſinne not onely out of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, but of a ſpirituall, for a naturall conſcience may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave him, for there be three degrees of conſcience.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Yet are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,</head>
               <item>Firſt, a prophaine man hath ſome conſcience,</item>
               <item>Secondly a civile man hath more conſcience,</item>
               <item>Thirdly a godly man hath moſt conſcience</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:6"/>Paul ſpeaketh of the heathen, that they had a conſcience that did accuſe excuſe them, but when a man doth not commit ſin, being enlightned by a ſpirituall conſcience, which is when a man hath a love to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary grace, and is caried with a certaine deſire to doe it (as men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate) though there were no reward, and hate the ſin and will not commit it, but a man may have a reſtraint from a naturall conſcience, yet it may have dominion over him, becauſe it is as a barking dog, that keeps the thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e robbing.</p>
            <list>
               <head>When a man</head>
               <item>Firſt doth not purpoſe to commit the ſin,</item>
               <item>Secondly hath reluctancy in the committing of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly grieveth afterwards, and riſeth with a bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>reſolution not to doe it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But if this proceeded from a naturall conſcience it is nothing, but if it proceed from a ſpirituall conſcience and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red of ſinne, this is a good ſigne.</p>
            <p>Nintly, when after ſtriving we have the victory, for we ſhal have the victory if we ſtrive aright, this taks way their excuſe, that ſay its their infirmities, but if they lye not in ſin, they wil have the victory over it, els thou art not a King, for a King is victorious, yet a King may have rebels, yea he may be wounded yet he keeps his power. So the ſaints may have many infirmities, yea they may have ſound failes, yet in the end they have the victory. God ſhall tread Satan under their feere wherefore the Godly mans heart though he faileth ſometimes is like a troubled fountaine, which though it be muddy, yet becauſe their is a ſpring of grace in his heart, it worketh it ſelfe pure againe, and works out all the mud, therefore content not your ſelves with diſlike of ſinne but leave not till you have got the victory.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Obſerve whether thou delighteſt in thoſe, commit the ſame ſins, if you doe you ly in ſin whatſoever you pretend, they doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>laſt,</hi>
               </note> theſe things, but have pleaſure in thoſe doe them which is a ſigne of a deſperate heart, for a man may be drawne to ſinne by paſſion, yet his heart may be upright, but when he alloweth, and loveth it another, then there is no paſſion to lead him, but its a ſigne his heart is bent to it, for its a ſigne of grace, when you love thoſe excell in grace, its a ſigne your hearts are good, ſo on the contrary its a ſigne of a corrupt and rotten heart, when wee rejoice in iniquity, as for example, ſuppoſe a man have a luſt of uncleannes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet diſliketh it on another, and liketh theſe that excell in the contrary vertue, and grace, its a ſigne he is in a good eſtate, and this is true, becauſe in another a man hath no paſſion
<pb facs="tcp:10940:6"/>
to leade him away.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, when a man ſhall commit a ſinne, cleane to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after perſwaſion, and long deliberation, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken from <hi>Ieroboam</hi> example <hi>Saul &amp; Ahab,</hi> theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted their ſinnes but once or twiſe as <hi>Saul</hi> had a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement from <hi>Samuel</hi> not to doe it, he had many dayes d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liberation upon it, yet he did which loſt him his ſoule. <hi>David</hi> committed greater ſins, yet God counted them nothing, becauſe he did not caſt God away but <hi>Saul</hi> had caſt off, ſo <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t up the calfe on deliberation and contrary to the perſwaſion of the prophet, therefore God caſt him off. This was <hi>Balams</hi> ſin who deliberated what he ſhuld doe, yet having a ſecret deſire of reward, did curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> which made God caſt him off, this was the ſin of <hi>Francis Spira</hi> who was ſmitten for committing of a ſin of deliberation.</p>
            <p>Thirteenely and laſtly, when a man ſhall make no conſcience of ſmal particular ſins, wherein his Iudgement is convicted that they are ſins, its a ſigne ſin hath dominion over him, this is plaine by ſcripture, he that is not faithfull in the greateſt, he may doe it, yet not be faithfull. Againe by reaſon, if a ſmall ſin be a ſin againſt God, then why make you conſcience of the leaſt, for God is offended with theſe as well as with the greateſt, ſo if ye make conſcience of the greateſt of the dutyes of Gods worſhip, why doe you not alſo of the leaſt duties? for God is<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> pleaſed with theſe, as well as with the other, ſome ſay they will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, but they need not be ſo preaſe as ſome ſcrupulous men are, but let them examine themſelves, if the leaſt ſins be ſinnes, they muſt alſo make conſcience of them, ſo if we muſt keep an houre of the Sabboth, there is the ſame reaſon of the reſt of the howres, ſo for idle ſpeeches, and faſhioning of themſelves to the world, ſo if wee ſeeke for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or riches, it is contrary to the commandement of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeke not to be rich, for they drowne themſelves in perdition and deſtruction, ſo wee muſt not keep company with evill and unſanctified men, examine how we practiſe this in all duties commanded, let us try our ſelves by abſtaining from occaſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether we re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raine our ſelves from the temptations of objects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for our ſpeech muſt be gracious, not by fits, but alwayes, ſo we muſt be diligent in our callings, if cut of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we doe this we are faithfull, otherwiſe we are not, for the ſame God which commanded not us to kil, commanded us not to commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, if then thou committeſt adultery thou offendeſt God, ſo Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s would not leave an hoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e behind him in Egypt, becauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him ſo to doe, know you not that no unrighteous man ſhall inherit the Kingdome of God, ſo if we abſtaine from ſoule ſinnes, yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 9, 4,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:7"/>
we commit the leaſt, we ſhall never goe to heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>It ſerves for in couragement for feareful chriſtians, for if it ſhall not <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> have dominion over you, then this may encourage you againſt the ſin that prevaileth againſt you ſometimes, but they ſhall have the victory, it is true that many ſins make warre againſt many chriſtians, and will not be overcome for a long tyme, it may be for one, two, or three years yet let us not be overcome, but renew our ſtrength againe, and in the end we ſhall have the victory.</p>
            <p>Thirdly we have heere priviledge of chriſtians, for though they be ſervants, while other be Princes, yet they are free in regard of their luſts, to ſee a man lead to his execution, we would not thinke it were for his honour, ſo when ungodly men thrive in their worldly luſts, then they lead his ſoule to his deſtruction, when ſinne ſhall have no domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the godly, but the ambitious and voluptuous men doe what ſoever their luſts commands them with a miſerable bondage, but the godly are free from ſinne.</p>
            <p>It is not enough for men to ſee their ſinnes, or to blame them in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
               </label> or to purpoſe to amend or forſake them, but they muſt ſtrive to overcome them, or elſe they ſhall have no promiſe of the goſpel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyd unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharoah</hi> was a wicked man, yet with heart he purpoſed to let the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael goe, but when ſome temptation aſſaulted him, then he would not let them goe, ſo <hi>Saul</hi> purpoſed in his heart not to kill <hi>David</hi> inſomuch that he ſware to <hi>Ionathan</hi> he would not doe it, yet afterward he attempted it upon another temptation, but we muſt come to feele that ſin hath no dominion over us, otherwiſe we ſhal heare that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Depart from m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ye wicked into everlasting fire, and out of thy owne mouth I will adjudge thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou wicked ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much may be ſufficient for the unfolding the firſt point of doctrine, proceed wee to a ſecond which flowes from hence alſo, and that is this, viz.</p>
            <p>That ſinne although it doe not raigne in the ſaints, yet doth<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mayne, and dwell in them, for proofe whereof ſee theſe places of ſcripture, <hi>if any man thinketh</hi> (ſaith Saint Iohn) <hi>that he hath no ſin, hee is a lyer, and there is no trueth in him,</hi> the trueth whereof will be ſeene in theſe things clearely.</p>
            <p>1. Beeauſe its knowledge is imperſect, and therefore everie grace as faith is imper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect, and ſo our love, and therefore ſo much ſinne muſt be in a man, in as much as his grace is not perfect.</p>
            <p>2 The fleſh luſteth after the ſpirit, therefore it is plaine there is ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:10940:7"/>
in us, yea ſo much that often times it even captivateth us.</p>
            <p>3. Wee have in this life but the firſt fruites of the ſpirit, now when wee ſhall have it in fulneſſe, we ſhall have no more than enough, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having now but the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, Mortification, &amp; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitication, ſinne is not wholly aboliſhed in the Saints in this life, but doth dwell in them.</p>
            <p>To humble us, and to make us ſee what is our hearts, and to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> make us know that the Lord bringeth us to the holy Land, therefore God ſometimes left the Iſraelites to trye them, and ſo hee troubled <hi>Hezechiah</hi> to know what was in his heart, and ſo hee ſent a Meſſinger of Satan to buffet S. <hi>Paul,</hi> leaſt hee ſhould bee exalted above meaſure through aboundance of Revelations, and ſo the Lord doth deale with everie Saint.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt may bee acknowledged, for if wee had no ſinne in us,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> we ſhould acknowledge the benefits of his mediation, ſo much as now wee doe, all are ſhut up under ſinne, that hee might have mercie upon<note place="margin">Rom, 3, 9,</note> all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 9. that is, that it might bee manifeſted and declared, that they are ſaved meerely by the mercie of God in Chriſt, as is ſaid after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, verſe the 26. otherwiſe we ſhould not rightly value our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſanctification, but ſeeing him ſubduing, pardoning our ſinnes, wee ſee what neede wee have of him, how that wee are loſt without him.</p>
            <p>That wee might exerciſe our faith. 1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 3. wee are the ſonnes <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> of God, but it doth not yet appeare what it ſhall bee, but &amp;c. ſo GOD hath hidde his children under baſeneſſe, that their faith might bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, for things wee ſee, we may eaſily believe, but faith is of things not ſeene, therefore God doth as men doe, hyde jewells under baſe places; where men would looke leaſt for them, wherefore wicked men ſtumble, and are offended at this, becauſe they doe not believe it, and therefore it is made an article of our faith, that wee neede, and believe the remiſſion, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: but let us apply it.</p>
            <p>1. This ſhould teach us not to be diſcouraged for thoſe infirmities that <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe, </seg>1</label> are in us, for there are ſuch in everie Saint, if he find he ſtriveth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and findeth ſuch ſucceſſe in it, ſinne is a gueſt to evill men, but a theefe to the godly, which they would not have come in their hearts, ſo it is one thing to weare a chaine as an ornament, and another as a fetter to reſtraine them, therefore they ought not to bee diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but to aſſure themſelves they are under grace:</p>
            <p>2. Wee muſt not cenſure men for theſe ſlippes and falls wee ſee in <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe, </seg>2</label> them, for wee muſt remember that ſinne dwelleth in them, wee muſt
<pb facs="tcp:10940:8"/>
not preſently judge them to bee hypocrites: <hi>Bee not many masters,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth <hi>S. Iames<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that is cenſure him not, for hee ſtandeth or falleth to his owne conſcience.</p>
            <p>3. This ſhould teach us to bee watchfull, and not to thinke our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 4, 4.</note> is at an end when we are in the ſtate of grace, for ſinne ſtill dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in us, and though wee have the victorie over ſinne one day, it will fight againſt us the next daye, as in a garden the weedes will grow, becauſe the rootes are not quite plucked up, and taken away, ſo ſinne is in us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore we muſt thinke it will fight againſt us and vexe us, and therefore I ſay, let us renue our ſtrength.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Now for this we muſt doe theſe two things.</head>
               <item>Firſt weaken ſinne.</item>
               <item>Secondly pray to God to make us watchfull.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And ſo I have alſo done with the ſecond doctrine, againe from the latter part of theſe words, or reaſon of the promiſe made unto them in in the former part of this verſe, that ſin ſhall not have dominion over them, becauſe they are not under the Law, but under grace, I gather this concluſion, viz.</p>
            <p>That the way to overcome ſinne, is to get aſſurance of the love and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct, </seg>
               </label> grace of God, and that it is forgiven them, the reaſon why the Apoſtle promiſes them ſin ſhall not have dominion over them, is becauſe they are not under the law but under grace, that is, they had aſſurance of Gods love, and that it is forgiven them, this is proved from that faith purifieth the heart, and you repent and believe the goſpell.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſons heereof are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe foure eſpecially,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Becauſe it is the meanes to get the ſpirit, without which no ſin is forgiven, which commeth by ſaith, for it is not receaved by the law, for ſo ſaith the apoſtle, receaved you the ſpirit by the works of the law <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> or by the deeds of faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the way to make us believe the promiſes, to make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we are transformed into a heavenly nature, for when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> the promiſes are true, that workes love in as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d love transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth us into the divine nature, without which no ſinne is overcome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly becauſe heereby we are able to reſiſt the tentations which <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> are either, for the injoying of good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eing of evill, ſo that theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes propound more good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then ſin can harme, ſinne threatned the love of outward things, but the promiſes propound eternall life, which is better then all things elſe in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:8"/>Fourthly, becauſe we doe delight in God, for when we doe believe in <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> God that our ſinnes are forgiven us in Chriſt, then wee looke at God, as on a mercy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull Father, and then wee ceaſe to delight in the world, &amp; we begin to delight our ſelves in the Lord.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, for direction to teach us the way how to heale a ſinne,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe, </seg>2</label> and that it is to get aſſurance that is pardoned &amp; forgiven, for legal ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours doe not heale a ſin, but is faith that purifies the heart, and purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pacifies it: as a Traytor will not come in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when he heares a procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for his death, but when he heares he ſhalllive and be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, this makes him to come in, ſo we when we only fixe our eyes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the legal terrours, we ſhall not heale our ſins, but when we belieue they are pardoned, this heales them.</p>
            <p>But ſorrow and a broken heart are required, for ſinners to be aſſured <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> of their forgivennes.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>This ſorrow is not ſo much commanded, but it is that whereby God prepareth his ſervants hearts, to make them ſee what need they have of pardon and ſo they may aske pardon, but the ſorrow commanded is that which followes beliefe, for the more I believe the promiſes, the more I ſhall grieve for diſpleaſing him.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>But what is the way to get aſſurance of the forgivennes of our ſins may ſome ſay?</p>
            <list>
               <head>I anſwere that that bee</head>
               <item>done which is to be done on our</item>
               <item>part.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label>
               </item>
               <item>believed which God hath promiſed</item>
            </list>
            <p>Q. The things to be done on our part, are theſe,</p>
            <p>Confeſſion plainely and truely wee muſt confeſſe them to God, and to man, when we our ſelves cannot overcome them,</p>
            <p>Secondly, contrition) which is when a man is not ſtubborne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth Gods will, and will pleaſe himſelfe, to get his heart broken, &amp;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> he ſaith as ſaint Paul ſaith. <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to doe?</hi> and then we are ſubject to his will, to him will I looke that is of a contrite heart.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, deſertion), or forſaking of ſin, for he that forſaketh not his ſins ſhall not proſper, which is when we having the like occaſions, yet<note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 6.</note> wil not give way to him but follow our owne luſts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That that bee believed which God hath promiſed, and that is, that as he hath ſaid; hee will forgive our ſins, upon ſuch and ſuch conditions, ſo we believe it, and to make us to doe this, theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may perſwade us.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Becauſe hee is mercyfull, in whoſe mercy there are three things,
<pb facs="tcp:10940:9"/>
all very materiall and moving,</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is natural to him, he is not wearying of ſhewing mercy, as the eye is not weary of ſeing, nor the eare in hearing, no more is God in ſhewing mercy, but in us it is not naturall, but an infuſed quality, and therefore we are weary when men provooke us often,</p>
            <p>Secondly his mercy is infinite, but in men it is not ſo, therefore come within compaſſe of this quality, and he will exerciſe it, for no ſin is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Gods mercy, this keepeth us from deſpaire, for though they be great, yet God is able to forgive them, as the raine watereth as well the great field as the little garden, and as the Sunne ſhines as well on mountaines, as on Molehills, and as it diſperſeth the thick miſt, as well as the leaſt thinne cloud, ſo doth Gods mercy paſſe by great ſinnes as well as little.</p>
            <p>But if our ſins be exceeding great, aggravated with circumſtances <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>
               </label> and often committed, then we cannot imagine that God will forgive us, This is anſwered by the Prophet Iſaiah, God is more mercyfull than<note place="margin">Sol.</note> man can be ſinfull, hee is more mercyfull than wee can imagine, my<note place="margin">Iſay, 55</note> thoughts are as much above your thoughts as the heaven is above the earth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly we ſee much mercy in men, and in the mother of a child, now it is but a drop out of the ocean of Gods mercy, but as a ſparke to the whole element of fire, if you being evill can give good things to your children, how much more ſhall your heavenly Father, &amp;c. ſee what the ſcripture ſaith, I <hi>am mercy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; ſin,</hi> the firſt word ſignifies originall ſinne, the ſecond actuall, the third rebellion, all which God can forgive.</p>
            <p>Secondly becauſe it is the end of Chriſts comming unto the world,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive, </seg>
               </label> now no man will doe any thing, eſpecially ſo great a matter as to kill himſelfe for no end, Chriſt then dyed for the forgivenes of ſins. This<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> ſaint Paul urgeth the end of Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, was to ſave ſinners, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the croſſe of Chriſt had beene of none effect, and his mediation of no uſe, if men did not commit ſinnes, or if God ſhould not forgive them, therefore God muſt needs be ready to forgive.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe God beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>echeth us to be reconciled, unto him throgh <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive, </seg>
               </label> Chriſt, now if God doth this, if we ſeeke earneſtly, he will heare us, the prodigall being willing to come home to his Father, he met him, and receaved him joyfully, ſo doth God, he chargeth his miniſters to compell men to come in: that is, to preach Gods mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he will forgive their ſinnes, and therefore the moſt acceptable action to God is to bring a ſinner to him:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:9"/>Fourthly. the charge laid on us to believe, we are charged on the paine of death to believe, and therefore it is moſt profitable for us, and moſt pleaſing to him, he takes it well at our hands, that we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve &amp; by the hand of faith lay hold on him, which he would not doe if hee were not ready to forgive,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh,</hi> 3. 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, from the examples of others, let us ſee what God hath done for them, and it will make us believe he forgave <hi>Manaſſes</hi> as well as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> he pardoned <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> as well as <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> he hath forgiven the greateſt ſins as well as the leaſt: and he will alſo deale ſo with us.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive: </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, from the effects of it which are theſe.</p>
            <p>Q. It glorifieth God much, Abraham believed, &amp; glorified God much for the greater the ſinner is, the more honour is given to God, as the phyſitian hath the greateſt glory by curing the greateſt wound, ſo God hath the greateſt glory by forgiving the greateſt ſinnes which wound the ſoule even to death.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It moveth us to love God the more, <hi>Mary</hi> loved much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe much was forgiven her.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it mollifies the moſt, it cauſeth them to relent, and weep much more, this is plaine, by that place, where it is ſaid, that when God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave the greateſt ſins then they mourned and lamented, as in theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts,</p>
            <p>Fourthly it purifies the heart, for no man lookes to keep his heart<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 2, 37<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> pure untill he be aſſured of the forgivennes of his ſinnes, for till then he cannot looke on God as on a father: but on the contrary, when the ſin is not forgiven, God looſeth the glory of being a father, and the glory of his trueth, and of his mercy, and that hardens the heart from relent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>7, from the price which was payed and which no ſin can goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive, </seg>
               </label> indeed if Chriſt had payed but a finite pryce, we feare that our ſins ſhould not be forgiven, if a man were in debt two thouſand pound and there were one payd, he might be diſcouraged, but when there is infinitly more payd then the debt is, this ſhould make us believe our ſins are forgiven us whatſoever they be, ſeing they be all but finit.</p>
            <p>Eightly from the tenour of the promiſes, which proclaime that they that believe and repent, and forſake their ſins, ſhall find pardon for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a King that proclames that all traitors, and rebels ſhall be pardoned if they would lay downe their weapons, now <hi>non est excipi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndum ubi lex non excipit,</hi> there is no exception to be made where the law maks none. God ſaith, yea therefore hath ſaid and ſworne it, that he will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give
<pb facs="tcp:10940:10"/>
our ſins, that we may believe it.</p>
            <p>But I have comitted the ſinne oft.</p>
            <p>Yet God will forgive thee, though thou haſt oft committed whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ </seg>
               </label> yet I will forgive thee, if thou tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne unto mee ſaith the Lord, by the Prophet of the houſe of Iſrael. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Hence then to make ſome uſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, as our uſe is, we may learne not to deceave our ſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o think we are in the ſtate of grace, when wee are not, for if we did truly believe our ſinnes are forgiven us, we wold <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
               </label> be healed, but if we have the ſame luſts, and keep the ſame company, which we did when we were not changed, it is a meere deluſion, what ſoever we ſay or thinke.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the third point too, there yet remaines one more behind, wherewith wee will conclude the whole text, and that wee may draw from the contrary, to what the Apoſtle heere ſaith, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is implyed, though not expreſt, for if ſin have no dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them that are not under the law but under grace, then on the other ſide muſt it needs be as true. viz</p>
            <p>That whoſoever is vnder the law, ſin hath dominion over him, that <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct, </seg>4</label> is, he that refraineth ſin only for feare of the law, and of judgemnets, ſin hath dominion over him, this is the caſe of them that refraine ſinning, only for feare and for the ſalvation of their ſoules, or for educations ſake, which have beene brought up in good families, or ſuch as repent upon ſome amazement, like the bulruſhes which hang downe their heads onely while the ſhowre laſts, and that,</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe all ſuch as are not under grace, but under the law have <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ, </seg>
               </label> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceaved the ſpirit, which commeth by hearing the goſpel, and no creature can change one creature into another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as lead unto gold, or a Wolfe unto a Lamb, unles it be by Gods ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſuch Gods ſervice is burthenſome, and violent motions laſt not long: they are weary in clamtering up an Hill, all naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſwiſter at the laſt then at the firſt, but theſe are like the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites who after a tyme, would have returned into AEGYPT againe.</p>
            <p>Now then to end all with the tyme, let us</p>
            <p>Q Bee exhorted not to abſtaine from any ſinne for feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but conſider whether thou wouldeſt ſerve God for Gods ſake although there were neither heaven nor hell; it muſt be our meat and drinke, which men would doe though there were no puniſhment for the omiſſion of it, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that hungereth and thirsteth after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10940:10"/>2. Hence we may learne not to deferre repentance till death, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, croſſes, or age ſomes, then it may be you would not ſin though with <hi>Balaam</hi> you had your houſefull of gold and ſilver, for its not the abſtinence from ſin that God loveth, but the change of the heart. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maziahs</hi> heart was not right though he walked in all the wayes of <hi>David,</hi> theſe are the men that have made a covenant with hell and death, but God will diſſanull that covenant, or it will be but equivocal, many have ſworne in their ſicknes never to commit ſin againe which afterward, they have committed againe with greedines, many have dyed in the ſame repentance.</p>
            <p>3. Labour to ſee your ſelves doing duties with as much love as you <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
               </label> can, and with as little feare, becauſe perfect love caſteth out feare, &amp; ſo beloved I have given you a briefe ſurvey of the ſeverall points con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the portion of holy Scripture, wherefore if you know theſe things, happy are yee if ye doe them, wherefore that yee may doe them, let us call upon God for a blesſing on what we have heard.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
